<?xml version="1.0" encoding="us-ascii"?>
  <?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt" ?>
  <!-- generated by https://github.com/cabo/kramdown-rfc2629 version 1.0.30 -->

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC0768 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.0768.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC0791 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.0791.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC0793 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.0793.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC1035 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1035.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC1122 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1122.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC1191 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1191.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3986 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3986.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4291 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4291.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4632 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4632.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4821 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4821.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5405 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5405.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8085 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8085.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5952 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5952.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-dots-architecture SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-dots-architecture.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-dots-use-cases SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-dots-use-cases.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3261 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3261.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7092 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7092.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4732 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4732.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4949 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4949.xml">
]>

<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="no"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>

<rfc docName="draft-ietf-dots-requirements-10" category="info">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="DOTS Requirements">Distributed Denial of Service (DDoS) Open Threat Signaling Requirements</title>

    <author initials="A." surname="Mortensen" fullname="Andrew Mortensen">
      <organization>Arbor Networks</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>2727 S. State St</street>
          <city>Ann Arbor, MI</city>
          <code>48104</code>
          <country>United States</country>
        </postal>
        <email>amortensen@arbor.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="R." surname="Moskowitz" fullname="Robert Moskowitz">
      <organization>Huawei</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>
          <city>Oak Park, MI</city>
          <code>42837</code>
          <country>United States</country>
        </postal>
        <email>rgm@htt-consult.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="T." surname="Reddy" fullname="Tirumaleswar Reddy">
      <organization>McAfee, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Embassy Golf Link Business Park</street>
          <city>Bangalore, Karnataka</city>
          <code>560071</code>
          <country>India</country>
        </postal>
        <email>TirumaleswarReddy_Konda@McAfee.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2018" month="January" day="02"/>

    <area>Security</area>
    <workgroup>DOTS</workgroup>
    <keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>

    <abstract>


<t>This document defines the requirements for the Distributed Denial of Service
(DDoS) Open Threat Signaling (DOTS) protocols coordinating attack response
against DDoS attacks.</t>



    </abstract>


  </front>

  <middle>


<section anchor="problems" title="Introduction">

<section anchor="context-and-motivation" title="Context and Motivation">
<t>Distributed Denial of Service (DDoS) attacks continue to plague network
operators around the globe, from Tier-1 service providers on down to enterprises
and small businesses. Attack scale and frequency similarly have continued to
increase, in part as a result of software vulnerabilities leading to reflection
and amplification attacks. High-volume attacks saturating inbound links are now
common, and the impact of larger-scale attacks attract the attention of
international press agencies.</t>

<t>The greater impact of contemporary DDoS attacks has led to increased focus on
coordinated attack response. Many institutions and enterprises lack the
resources or expertise to operate on-premises attack mitigation solutions
themselves, or simply find themselves constrained by local bandwidth
limitations. To address such gaps, security service providers have begun to
offer on-demand traffic scrubbing services, which aim to separate the DDoS
traffic from legitimate traffic and forward only the latter. Today each such
service offers a proprietary invocation interface for subscribers to request attack mitigation,
tying subscribers to proprietary signaling implementations while also limiting
the subset of network elements capable of participating in the attack mitigation.
As a result of signaling interface incompatibility, attack responses may be
fragmentary or otherwise incomplete, leaving key players in the attack path
unable to assist in the defense.</t>

<t>The lack of a common method to coordinate a real-time response among involved
actors and network domains inhibits the speed and effectiveness of DDoS attack
mitigation. This document describes the required characteristics of protocols
enabling requests for DDoS attack mitigation, reducing attack impact and leading
to more efficient defensive strategies.</t>

<t>DDoS Open Threat Signaling (DOTS) communicates the need for defensive action in anticipation of or in
response to an attack, but does not dictate the form any defensive action
takes. DOTS supplements calls for help with pertinent details about the detected
attack, allowing entities participating in DOTS to form ad hoc, adaptive
alliances against DDoS attacks as described in the DOTS use cases
<xref target="I-D.ietf-dots-use-cases"></xref>. The requirements in this document are derived from
those use cases and <xref target="I-D.ietf-dots-architecture"></xref>.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="terminology" title="Terminology">

<t>The key words &ldquo;MUST&rdquo;, &ldquo;MUST NOT&rdquo;, &ldquo;REQUIRED&rdquo;, &ldquo;SHALL&rdquo;, &ldquo;SHALL NOT&rdquo;,
&ldquo;SHOULD&rdquo;, &ldquo;SHOULD NOT&rdquo;, &ldquo;RECOMMENDED&rdquo;, &ldquo;MAY&rdquo;, and &ldquo;OPTIONAL&rdquo; in this
document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119"/>.</t>

<t>This document adopts the following terms:</t>

<t><list style="hanging">
  <t hangText='DDoS:'>
  A distributed denial-of-service attack, in which traffic originating from
multiple sources are directed at a target on a network. DDoS attacks are
intended to cause a negative impact on the availability of servers, services,
applications, and/or other functionality of an attack target.
Denial-of-service considerations are discussed in detail in <xref target="RFC4732"></xref>.</t>
  <t hangText='DDoS attack target:'>
  A network connected entity with a finite set of resources, such as network
bandwidth, memory or CPU, that is the target of a DDoS attack. Potential
targets include (but are not limited to) network elements, network links, servers, and services.</t>
  <t hangText='DDoS attack telemetry:'>
  Collected measurements and behavioral characteristics defining the nature of a
DDoS attack.</t>
  <t hangText='Countermeasure:'>
  An action or set of actions taken to recognize and filter out DDoS attack
traffic while passing legitimate traffic to the attack target.</t>
  <t hangText='Mitigation:'>
  A set of countermeasures enforced against traffic destined for the target or
targets of a detected or reported DDoS attack, where countermeasure
enforcement is managed by an entity in the network path between attack sources
and the attack target. Mitigation methodology is out of scope for this
document.</t>
  <t hangText='Mitigator:'>
  An entity, typically a network element, capable of performing mitigation of a
detected or reported DDoS attack. For the purposes of this document, this
entity is a black box capable of mitigation, making no assumptions about
availability or design of countermeasures, nor about the programmable
interface(s) between this entity and other network elements. The mitigator and
invoked DOTS server are assumed to belong to the same administrative entity.</t>
  <t hangText='DOTS client:'>
  A DOTS-aware software module responsible for requesting attack response
coordination with other DOTS-aware elements.</t>
  <t hangText='DOTS server:'>
  A DOTS-aware software module handling and responding to messages from DOTS
clients. The DOTS server enables mitigation on behalf of the DOTS
client, if requested, by communicating the DOTS client&rsquo;s request to the
mitigator and returning selected mitigator feedback to the requesting DOTS
client. A DOTS server may also be colocated with a mitigator.</t>
  <t hangText='DOTS agent:'>
  Any DOTS-aware software module capable of participating in a DOTS signal
or data channel. It can be a DOTS client, DOTS server, or, as a logical agent,
a DOTS gateway.</t>
  <t hangText='DOTS gateway:'>
  A DOTS-aware software module resulting from the logical concatenation of a
DOTS server and a DOTS client, analogous to a Session Initiation Protocol
(SIP) <xref target="RFC3261"></xref> Back-to-Back User Agent (B2BUA) <xref target="RFC7092"></xref>. A DOTS gateway has
a client-facing side, which behaves as a DOTS server for downstream clients,
and a server-facing side, which performs the role of DOTS client to upstream
DOTS servers. Client-domain DOTS gateways are DOTS gateways that are in the
DOTS client&rsquo;s domain, while server-domain DOTS gateways denote DOTS gateways
that are in the DOTS server&rsquo;s domain. DOTS gateways are described further in
<xref target="I-D.ietf-dots-architecture"></xref>.</t>
  <t hangText='Signal channel:'>
  A bidirectional, mutually authenticated communication channel between two DOTS
agents characterized by resilience even in conditions leading to severe
packet loss, such as a volumetric DDoS attack causing network congestion.</t>
  <t hangText='DOTS signal:'>
  A concise authenticated status/control message transmitted between DOTS
agents, used to indicate the client&rsquo;s need for mitigation, as well as to convey
the status of any requested mitigation.</t>
  <t hangText='Heartbeat:'>
  A message transmitted between DOTS agents over the signal channel, used as a
keep-alive and to measure peer health.</t>
  <t hangText='Data channel:'>
  A secure communication layer between two DOTS agents used for
infrequent bulk exchange of data not easily or appropriately communicated
through the signal channel under attack conditions.</t>
  <t hangText='Filter:'>
  A specification of a matching network traffic flow or set of flows. The filter will typically have a policy associated with it, e.g., rate-limiting or discarding matching traffic <xref target="RFC4949"></xref>.</t>
  <t hangText='Blacklist:'>
  A filter list of addresses, prefixes, and/or other identifiers indicating
sources from which traffic should be blocked, regardless of traffic content.</t>
  <t hangText='Whitelist:'>
  A list of addresses, prefixes, and/or other identifiers indicating sources
from which traffic should always be allowed, regardless of contradictory data
gleaned in a detected attack.</t>
  <t hangText='Multi-homed DOTS client:'>
  A DOTS client exchanging messages with multiple DOTS servers, each in a
separate administrative domain.</t>
</list></t>

</section>
</section>
<section anchor="requirements" title="Requirements">

<t>This section describes the required features and characteristics of the DOTS
protocols.</t>

<t>The DOTS protocols enable and manage mitigation on behalf of a network domain or
resource which is or may become the focus of a DDoS attack. An active DDoS
attack against the entity controlling the DOTS client need not be present before
establishing a communication channel between DOTS agents. Indeed, establishing a
relationship with peer DOTS agents during normal network conditions provides the
foundation for more rapid attack response against future attacks, as all
interactions setting up DOTS, including any business or service level
agreements, are already complete. Reachability information of peer DOTS agents
is provisioned to a DOTS client using a variety of manual or dynamic methods.</t>

<t>The DOTS protocol must at a minimum make it possible for a DOTS client to
request a mitigator&rsquo;s aid mounting a defense, coordinated by a DOTS server,
against a suspected attack, signaling within or between domains as requested by
local operators. DOTS clients should similarly be able to withdraw aid requests.
DOTS requires no justification from DOTS clients for requests for help, nor do
DOTS clients need to justify withdrawing help requests: the decision is local to
the DOTS clients&rsquo; domain. Multi-homed DOTS clients must be able to select the
appropriate DOTS server(s) to which a mitigation request is to be sent. Further
multi-homing considerations are out of scope.</t>

<t>Regular feedback between DOTS clients and DOTS servers supplement the defensive
alliance by maintaining a common understanding of the DOTS agents&rsquo; health and
activity. Bidirectional communication between DOTS clients and DOTS servers is
therefore critical.</t>

<t>DOTS protocol implementations face competing operational goals when maintaining
this bidirectional communication stream.  On the one hand, the protocol must be
resilient under extremely hostile network conditions, providing continued
contact between DOTS agents even as attack traffic saturates the link. Such
resiliency may be developed several ways, but characteristics such as small
message size, asynchronous, redundant message delivery and minimal connection
overhead (when possible given local network policy) will tend to contribute to
the robustness demanded by a viable DOTS protocol. Operators of peer
DOTS-enabled domains may enable quality- or class-of-service traffic tagging to
increase the probability of successful DOTS signal delivery, but DOTS does not require
such policies be in place. The DOTS solution indeed must be viable especially
in their absence.</t>

<t>On the other hand, DOTS must include protections ensuring message
confidentiality, integrity and authenticity to keep the protocol from becoming
another vector for the very attacks it&rsquo;s meant to help fight off. DOTS clients
must be able to authenticate DOTS servers, and vice versa, to avoid exposing new
attack surfaces when deploying DOTS; specifically, to prevent DDoS mitigation in
response to DOTS signaling from becoming a new form of attack. In order to
provide this level of protection, DOTS agents must have a way to negotiate and
agree upon the terms of protocol security. Attacks against the transport
protocol should not offer a means of attack against the message confidentiality,
integrity and authenticity.</t>

<t>The DOTS server and client must also have some common method of defining the
scope of any mitigation performed by a mitigator, as well as making
adjustments to other commonly configurable features, such as targeted port
numbers, exchanging black- and white-lists, and so on.</t>

<t>Finally, DOTS should be sufficiently extensible to meet future needs in
coordinated attack defense, although this consideration is necessarily
superseded by the other operational requirements.</t>

<section anchor="general-requirements" title="General Requirements">

<t><list style="hanging">
  <t hangText='GEN-001'>
  Extensibility: Protocols and data models developed as part of DOTS MUST be
extensible in order to keep DOTS adaptable to operational and proprietary
DDoS defenses. Future extensions MUST be backward compatible. DOTS protocols
MUST use a version number system to distinguish protocol revisions.
Implementations of older protocol versions SHOULD ignore information added
to DOTS messages as part of newer protocol versions.</t>
  <t hangText='GEN-002'>
  Resilience and Robustness: The signaling protocol MUST be designed to maximize
the probability of signal delivery even under the severely constrained network
conditions imposed by particular attack traffic. The protocol MUST be
resilient, that is, continue operating despite message loss and out-of-order
or redundant message delivery. In support of signaling protocol robustness,
DOTS signals SHOULD be conveyed over a transport not susceptible to
Head of Line Blocking.</t>
  <t hangText='GEN-003'>
  Bidirectionality: To support peer health detection, to maintain an open
signal channel, and to increase the probability of signal delivery during
an attack, the signal channel MUST be bidirectional, with client and server
transmitting signals to each other at regular intervals, regardless of any
client request for mitigation. Unidirectional messages MUST be supported
within the bidirectional signal channel to allow for unsolicited message
delivery, enabling asynchronous notifications between DOTS agents.</t>
  <t hangText='GEN-004'>
  Bulk Data Exchange: Infrequent bulk data exchange between DOTS agents can also
significantly augment attack response coordination, permitting such tasks as
population of black- or white-listed source addresses; address or prefix group
aliasing; exchange of incident reports; and other hinting or configuration
supplementing attack response.</t>
  <t>As the resilience requirements for the DOTS signal channel mandate small
signal message size, a separate, secure data channel utilizing a reliable
transport protocol MUST be used for bulk data exchange.</t>
</list></t>

</section>
<section anchor="signal-channel-requirements" title="Signal Channel Requirements">

<t><list style="hanging">
  <t hangText='SIG-001'>
  Use of Common Transport Protocols: DOTS MUST operate over common widely
deployed and standardized transport protocols. While connectionless transport
such as the User Datagram Protocol (UDP) <xref target="RFC0768"/> SHOULD be used for the
signal channel, the Transmission Control Protocol (TCP) <xref target="RFC0793"></xref> MAY be used
if necessary due to network policy or middlebox capabilities or
configurations.</t>
  <t hangText='SIG-002'>
  Sub-MTU Message Size: To avoid message fragmentation and the consequently
decreased probability of message delivery over a congested link, signaling
protocol message size MUST be kept under signaling Path Maximum Transmission
Unit (PMTU), including the byte overhead of any encapsulation, transport
headers, and transport- or message-level security.</t>
  <t>DOTS agents SHOULD attempt to learn the PMTU through mechanisms such as Path
MTU Discovery <xref target="RFC1191"></xref> or Packetization Layer Path MTU Discovery <xref target="RFC4821"></xref>.
If the PMTU cannot be discovered, DOTS agents SHOULD assume a PMTU of 1280
bytes.  If IPv4 support on legacy or otherwise unusual networks is a
consideration and PMTU is unknown, DOTS implementations MAY rely on a PMTU of
576 bytes, as discussed in <xref target="RFC0791"></xref> and <xref target="RFC1122"></xref>.</t>
  <t hangText='SIG-003'>
  Channel Health Monitoring: DOTS agents MUST support exchange of heartbeat
messages over the signal channel to monitor channel health. Peer DOTS agents
SHOULD regularly send heartbeats to each other while a mitigation request is
active. The heartbeat interval during active mitigation is not specified, but
SHOULD be frequent enough to maintain any on-path NAT or Firewall bindings during
mitigation.</t>
  <t>To support scenarios in which loss of heartbeat is used to trigger
mitigation, and to keep the channel active, DOTS clients MAY solicit heartbeat
exchanges after successful mutual authentication. When DOTS agents are
exchanging heartbeats and no mitigation request is active, either agent MAY
request changes to the heartbeat rate. For example, a DOTS server might want
to reduce heartbeat frequency or cease heartbeat exchanges when an active DOTS
client has not requested mitigation, in order to control load.</t>
  <t>Following mutual authentication, a signal channel MUST be considered active
until a DOTS agent explicitly ends the session, or either DOTS agent fails to
receive heartbeats from the other after a mutually agreed upon retransmission
procedure has been exhausted. Because heartbeat loss is much more likely
during volumetric attack, DOTS agents SHOULD avoid signal channel termination
when mitigation is active and heartbeats are not received by either DOTS agent
for an extended period. In such circumstances, DOTS clients MAY attempt to
reestablish the signal channel, but SHOULD continue to send heartbeats so that
the DOTS server knows the session is still alive. DOTS servers
SHOULD monitor the attack, using feedback from the mitigator and other
available sources, and MAY use the absence of attack traffic and lack of
client heartbeats as an indication the signal channel is defunct.</t>
  <t hangText='SIG-004'>
  Channel Redirection: In order to increase DOTS operational flexibility and
scalability, DOTS servers SHOULD be able to redirect DOTS clients to another
DOTS server at any time. DOTS clients MUST NOT assume the redirection target
DOTS server shares security state with the redirecting DOTS server. DOTS
clients MAY attempt abbreviated security negotiation methods supported by the
protocol, such as DTLS session resumption, but MUST be prepared to negotiate
new security state with the redirection target DOTS server.</t>
  <t>Due to the increased likelihood of packet loss caused by link congestion
during an attack, DOTS servers SHOULD NOT redirect while mitigation is enabled
during an active attack against a target in the DOTS client&rsquo;s domain.</t>
  <t hangText='SIG-005'>
  Mitigation Requests and Status:
Authorized DOTS clients MUST be able to request scoped mitigation from DOTS
servers. DOTS servers MUST send mitigation request status in response to
granted DOTS clients requests for mitigation. If a DOTS server rejects an
authorized request for mitigation, the DOTS server MUST include a reason for
the rejection in the status message sent to the client.</t>
  <t>Due to the higher likelihood of packet loss during a DDoS attack, DOTS
servers SHOULD regularly send mitigation status to authorized DOTS clients
which have requested and been granted mitigation, regardless of client
requests for mitigation status.</t>
  <t>When DOTS client-requested mitigation is active, DOTS server status messages
SHOULD include the following mitigation metrics:
      <list style="symbols">
        <t>Total number of packets blocked by the mitigation</t>
        <t>Current number of packets per second blocked</t>
        <t>Total number of bytes blocked</t>
        <t>Current number of bytes per second blocked</t>
      </list>
  </t>
  <t>DOTS clients MAY take these metrics into account when determining whether
to ask the DOTS server to cease mitigation.</t>
  <t>A DOTS client MAY withdraw a mitigation request at any time, regardless of
whether mitigation is currently active. The DOTS server MUST immediately
acknowledge a DOTS client&rsquo;s request to stop mitigation.</t>
  <t>To protect against route or DNS flapping caused by a client rapidly toggling
mitigation, and to dampen the effect of oscillating attacks, DOTS servers MAY
allow mitigation to continue for a limited period after acknowledging a DOTS
client&rsquo;s withdrawal of a mitigation request. During this period, DOTS server
status messages SHOULD indicate that mitigation is active but terminating.</t>
  <t>The initial active-but-terminating period is implementation- and deployment-
specific, but SHOULD be sufficiently long to absorb latency incurred by route
propagation. If the client requests mitigation again before the initial
active-but-terminating period elapses, the DOTS server MAY exponentially
increase the active-but-terminating period up to a maximum of 300 seconds (5
minutes). After the active-but-terminating period elapses, the DOTS server
MUST treat the mitigation as terminated, as the DOTS client is no longer
responsible for the mitigation. For example, if there is a financial
relationship between the DOTS client and server domains, the DOTS client
ceases incurring cost at this point.</t>
  <t hangText='SIG-006'>
  Mitigation Lifetime: DOTS servers MUST support mitigation lifetimes, and
MUST terminate a mitigation when the lifetime elapses. DOTS servers also MUST
support renewal of mitigation lifetimes in mitigation requests from DOTS
clients, allowing clients to extend mitigation as necessary for the duration
of an attack.</t>
  <t>DOTS servers MUST treat a mitigation terminated due to lifetime expiration
exactly as if the DOTS client originating the mitigation had asked to end the
mitigation, including the active-but-terminating period, as described above
in SIG-005.</t>
  <t>DOTS clients MUST include a mitigation lifetime in all mitigation requests.</t>
  <t>DOTS servers SHOULD support indefinite mitigation lifetimes, enabling
architectures in which the mitigator is always in the traffic path to the
resources for which the DOTS client is requesting protection. DOTS clients
MUST be prepared to not be granted mitigations with indefinite lifetimes. DOTS
servers MAY refuse mitigations with indefinite lifetimes, for policy reasons.
The reasons themselves are out of scope. If the DOTS server does not grant a
mitigation request with an indefinite mitigation lifetime, it MUST set the
lifetime to a value that is configured locally. That value MUST be returned in
a reply to the requesting DOTS client.</t>
  <t hangText='SIG-007'>
  Mitigation Scope: DOTS clients MUST indicate desired mitigation scope. The
scope type will vary depending on the resources requiring mitigation. All DOTS
agent implementations MUST support the following required scope types:

      <list style="symbols">
        <t>IPv4 prefixes in CIDR notation <xref target="RFC4632"></xref></t>
        <t>IPv6 prefixes <xref target="RFC4291"></xref><xref target="RFC5952"/></t>
        <t>Domain names <xref target="RFC1035"></xref></t>
      </list>
  </t>
  <t>The following mitigation scope types are OPTIONAL:
      <list style="symbols">
        <t>Uniform Resource Identifiers <xref target="RFC3986"></xref></t>
      </list>
  </t>
  <t>DOTS servers MUST be able to resolve domain names and (when supported) URIs. How name
resolution is managed on the DOTS server is implementation-specific.</t>
  <t>DOTS agents MUST support mitigation scope aliases, allowing DOTS clients and
servers to refer to collections of protected resources by an opaque identifier
created through the data channel, direct configuration, or other means. Domain
name and URI mitigation scopes may be thought of as a form of scope alias, in
which the addresses to which the domain name or URI resolve represent the full
scope of the mitigation.</t>
  <t>If there is additional information available narrowing the scope of any
requested attack response, such as targeted port range, protocol, or service,
DOTS clients SHOULD include that information in client mitigation requests.
DOTS clients MAY also include additional attack details. DOTS servers MAY
ignore such supplemental information when enabling countermeasures on the
mitigator.</t>
  <t>As an active attack evolves, DOTS clients MUST be able to adjust as necessary
the scope of requested mitigation by refining the scope of resources requiring
mitigation.</t>
  <t>A DOTS client may obtain the mitigation scope through direct provisioning
or through implementation-specific methods of discovery. DOTS clients MUST
support at least one mechanism to obtain mitigation scope.</t>
  <t hangText='SIG-008'>
  Mitigation Efficacy: When a mitigation request is active, DOTS clients SHOULD
transmit a metric of perceived mitigation efficacy to the DOTS server. DOTS
servers MAY use the efficacy metric to adjust countermeasures activated on a
mitigator on behalf of a DOTS client.</t>
  <t hangText='SIG-009'>
  Conflict Detection and Notification: Multiple DOTS clients controlled by a
single administrative entity may send conflicting mitigation requests for pools
of protected resources as a result of misconfiguration, operator error, or
compromised DOTS clients. DOTS servers in the same administrative domain
attempting to honor conflicting requests may flap network route or DNS
information, degrading the networks attempting to participate in attack
response with the DOTS clients. DOTS servers in a single administrative domain
SHALL detect such conflicting requests, and SHALL notify the DOTS clients in
conflict. The notification SHOULD indicate the nature and scope of the
conflict, for example, the overlapping prefix range in a conflicting
mitigation request.</t>
  <t hangText='SIG-010:'>
  Network Address Translator Traversal: DOTS clients may be deployed behind a
Network Address Translator (NAT), and need to communicate with DOTS servers
through the NAT. DOTS protocols MUST therefore be capable of traversing NATs.</t>
  <t>If UDP is used as the transport for the DOTS signal channel, all
considerations in &ldquo;Middlebox Traversal Guidelines&rdquo; in <xref target="RFC8085"></xref> apply to DOTS.
Regardless of transport, DOTS protocols MUST follow established best common
practices (BCPs) for NAT traversal.</t>
</list></t>

</section>
<section anchor="data-channel-requirements" title="Data Channel Requirements">

<t>The data channel is intended to be used for bulk data exchanges between DOTS
agents. Unlike the signal channel, which must operate nominally even when
confronted with signal degradation due to significant packet loss, the data channel is not
expected to be constructed to deal with attack conditions.  As the primary
function of the data channel is data exchange, a reliable transport is required
in order for DOTS agents to detect data delivery success or failure.</t>

<t>The DOTS data channel protocol MUST be extensible. We anticipate the data
channel will be used for such purposes as configuration or resource discovery.
For example, a DOTS client may submit to a DOTS server a collection of
prefixes it wants to refer to by alias when requesting mitigation, to which the
server would respond with a success status and the new prefix group alias, or an
error status and message in the event the DOTS client&rsquo;s data channel request
failed. The transactional nature of such data exchanges suggests a separate set
of requirements for the data channel, while the potentially sensitive content
sent between DOTS agents requires extra precautions to ensure data privacy and
authenticity.</t>

<t><list style="hanging">
  <t hangText='DATA-001'>
  Reliable transport: Messages sent over the data channel MUST be delivered
reliably, in order sent.</t>
  <t hangText='DATA-002'>
  Data privacy and integrity: Transmissions over the data channel are likely to
contain operationally or privacy-sensitive information or instructions from
the remote DOTS agent. Theft or modification of data channel transmissions
could lead to information leaks or malicious transactions on behalf of the
sending agent (see <xref target="security-considerations"/> below). Consequently data sent
over the data channel MUST be encrypted and authenticated using current
industry best practices.  DOTS servers MUST enable means to prevent leaking
operationally or privacy-sensitive data. Although administrative entities
participating in DOTS may detail what data may be revealed to third-party DOTS
agents, such considerations are not in scope for this document.</t>
  <t hangText='DATA-003'>
  Resource Configuration: To help meet the general and signal channel
requirements in <xref target="signal-channel-requirements"/>, DOTS server implementations
MUST provide an interface to configure resource identifiers, as described in
SIG-007.

DOTS server implementations MAY expose additional configurability. Additional
configurability is implementation-specific.</t>
  <t hangText='DATA-004'>
  Black- and whitelist management: DOTS servers MUST provide methods for
DOTS clients to manage black- and white-lists of traffic destined for
resources belonging to a client.</t>
  <t>For example, a DOTS client should be able to create a black- or whitelist
entry, retrieve a list of current entries from either list, update the content
of either list, and delete entries as necessary.</t>
  <t>How a DOTS server authorizes DOTS client management of black- and white-list
entries is implementation-specific.</t>
</list></t>

</section>
<section anchor="security-requirements" title="Security Requirements">

<t>DOTS must operate within a particularly strict security context, as an
insufficiently protected signal or data channel may be subject to abuse,
enabling or supplementing the very attacks DOTS purports to mitigate.</t>

<t><list style="hanging">
  <t hangText='SEC-001'>
  Peer Mutual Authentication: DOTS agents MUST authenticate each other before a
DOTS signal or data channel is considered valid. The method of authentication
is not specified, but should follow current industry best practices with
respect to any cryptographic mechanisms to authenticate the remote peer.</t>
  <t hangText='SEC-002'>
  Message Confidentiality, Integrity and Authenticity: DOTS protocols MUST take
steps to protect the confidentiality, integrity and authenticity of messages
sent between client and server. While specific transport- and message-level
security options are not specified, the protocols MUST follow current industry
best practices for encryption and message authentication.</t>
  <t>In order for DOTS protocols to remain secure despite advancements in
cryptanalysis and traffic analysis, DOTS agents MUST be able to negotiate the
terms and mechanisms of protocol security, subject to the interoperability and
signal message size requirements above.</t>
  <t>While the interfaces between downstream DOTS server and upstream DOTS client
within a DOTS gateway are implementation-specific, those interfaces
nevertheless MUST provide security equivalent to that of the signal channels
bridged by gateways in the signaling path. For example, when a DOTS gateway
consisting of a DOTS server and DOTS client is running on the same logical
device, the two DOTS agents could be implemented within the same process
security boundary.</t>
  <t hangText='SEC-003'>
  Message Replay Protection: To prevent a passive attacker from capturing and
replaying old messages, and thereby potentially disrupting or influencing the
network policy of the receiving DOTS agent&rsquo;s domain, DOTS protocols MUST
provide a method for replay detection and prevention.</t>
  <t>Within the signal channel, messages MUST be uniquely identified such that
replayed or duplicated messages can be detected and discarded. Unique
mitigation requests MUST be processed at most once.</t>
  <t hangText='SEC-004'>
  Authorization: DOTS servers MUST authorize all messages from DOTS clients
which pertain to mitigation, configuration, filtering, or status.</t>
  <t>DOTS servers MUST reject mitigation requests with scopes which the DOTS client
is not authorized to manage.</t>
  <t>Likewise, DOTS servers MUST refuse to allow creation, modification or deletion
of scope aliases and black-/white-lists when the DOTS client is unauthorized.</t>
  <t>The modes of authorization are implementation-specific.</t>
</list></t>

</section>
<section anchor="data-model-requirements" title="Data Model Requirements">

<t>The value of DOTS is in standardizing a mechanism to permit elements, networks
or domains under threat of DDoS attack to request aid mitigating the
effects of any such attack. A well-structured DOTS data model is therefore
critical to the development of successful DOTS protocols.</t>

<t><list style="hanging">
  <t hangText='DM-001:'>
  Structure: The data model structure for the DOTS protocol may be described by
a single module, or be divided into related collections of hierarchical
modules and sub-modules. If the data model structure is split across modules,
those distinct modules MUST allow references to describe the overall data
model&rsquo;s structural dependencies.</t>
  <t hangText='DM-002:'>
  Versioning: To ensure interoperability between DOTS protocol implementations,
data models MUST be versioned. How the protocols represent data model versions
is not defined in this document.</t>
  <t hangText='DM-003:'>
  Mitigation Status Representation: The data model MUST provide the ability to
represent a request for mitigation and the withdrawal of such a request. The
data model MUST also support a representation of currently requested
mitigation status, including failures and their causes.</t>
  <t hangText='DM-004:'>
  Mitigation Scope Representation: The data model MUST support representation of
a requested mitigation&rsquo;s scope. As mitigation scope may be represented in
several different ways, per SIG-007 above, the data model MUST be capable of
flexible representation of mitigation scope.</t>
  <t hangText='DM-005:'>
  Mitigation Lifetime Representation: The data model MUST support representation
of a mitigation request&rsquo;s lifetime, including mitigations with no specified
end time.</t>
  <t hangText='DM-006:'>
  Mitigation Efficacy Representation: The data model MUST support representation
of a DOTS client&rsquo;s understanding of the efficacy of a mitigation enabled
through a mitigation request.</t>
  <t hangText='DM-007:'>
  Acceptable Signal Loss Representation: The data model MUST be able to
represent the DOTS agent&rsquo;s preference for acceptable signal loss when
establishing a signal channel, as described in GEN-002.</t>
  <t hangText='DM-008:'>
  Heartbeat Interval Representation: The data model MUST be able to represent
the DOTS agent&rsquo;s preferred heartbeat interval, which the client may include
when establishing the signal channel, as described in SIG-003.</t>
  <t hangText='DM-009:'>
  Relationship to Transport: The DOTS data model MUST NOT depend on the
specifics of any transport to represent fields in the model.</t>
</list></t>

</section>
</section>
<section anchor="congestion-control-considerations" title="Congestion Control Considerations">

<section anchor="signal-channel" title="Signal Channel">

<t>As part of a protocol expected to operate over links affected by DDoS attack
traffic, the DOTS signal channel MUST NOT contribute significantly to link
congestion. To meet the signal channel requirements above, DOTS signal channel
implementations SHOULD support connectionless transports. However, some
connectionless transports when deployed naively can be a source of network
congestion, as discussed in <xref target="RFC5405"></xref>. Signal channel implementations using such
connectionless transports, such as UDP, therefore MUST include a congestion
control mechanism.</t>

<t>Signal channel implementations using TCP may rely on built-in TCP congestion
control support.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="data-channel" title="Data Channel">
<t>As specified in DATA-001, the data channel requires reliable, in-order message
delivery. Data channel implementations using TCP may rely on the TCP
implementation&rsquo;s built-in congestion control mechanisms.</t>

</section>
</section>
<section anchor="security-considerations" title="Security Considerations">

<t>DOTS is at risk from three primary attacks:</t>

<t><list style="symbols">
  <t>DOTS agent impersonation</t>
  <t>Traffic injection</t>
  <t>Signaling blocking</t>
</list></t>

<t>The DOTS protocol MUST be designed for minimal data transfer to address the
blocking risk. Impersonation and traffic injection mitigation can be managed
through current secure communications best practices. See
<xref target="security-requirements"/> above for a detailed discussion.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="contributors" title="Contributors">

<t><list style="hanging">
  <t hangText='Mohamed Boucadair'><vspace blankLines='0'/>
  Orange</t>
  <t>mohamed.boucadair@orange.com</t>
</list></t>

<t><list style="hanging">
  <t hangText='Flemming Andreasen'><vspace blankLines='0'/>
  Cisco Systems, Inc.</t>
  <t>fandreas@cisco.com</t>
</list></t>

<t><list style="hanging">
  <t hangText='Dave Dolson'><vspace blankLines='0'/>
  Sandvine</t>
  <t>ddolson@sandvine.com</t>
</list></t>

</section>
<section anchor="acknowledgments" title="Acknowledgments">

<t>Thanks to Roman Danyliw and Matt Richardson for careful reading and feedback.</t>

</section>


  </middle>

  <back>

    <references title='Normative References'>

&RFC0768;
&RFC0791;
&RFC0793;
&RFC1035;
&RFC1122;
&RFC1191;
&RFC2119;
&RFC3986;
&RFC4291;
&RFC4632;
&RFC4821;
&RFC5405;
&RFC8085;
&RFC5952;


    </references>

    <references title='Informative References'>

&I-D.ietf-dots-architecture;
&I-D.ietf-dots-use-cases;
&RFC3261;
&RFC7092;
&RFC4732;
&RFC4949;


    </references>



  </back>
</rfc>

